<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jishnurajendran.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jishnurajendran.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-02-25T16:57:50+00:00</updated><id>https://jishnurajendran.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Ultrastrong Coupling in Quantum Computation</title><link href="https://jishnurajendran.github.io/blog/2025/USC/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ultrastrong Coupling in Quantum Computation"/><published>2025-02-18T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-18T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jishnurajendran.github.io/blog/2025/USC</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jishnurajendran.github.io/blog/2025/USC/"><![CDATA[<p>The ultrastrong coupling(USC) regime, where light-matter coupling is comparable to or even greater than the natural frequencies of the system. In this regime, the system no longer follows the Jaynes-Cummings model, showcasing new novel . The advancement of USC applications into superconducting circuits and trapped ions systems provides us with exciting challenges which drives the field closer to the quantum computation era.</p> <pre><code class="language-mermaid">---
config:
  theme: mc
---
mindmap
  root["Ultrastrong Coupling (USC)"]
    Improvements Enabled
      Fast Quantum Gate Operation
      Scalable Architecture
    Superconducting Circuits
      Advantages
        Boosted Effective Couplings
        Frequency Engineering
        Material Flexibility
      Disadvantages
        Decoherence Sensitivity
        Control Complexity
        Fabrication Challenges
    Trapped Ions
      Advantages
        High-Fidelity Gates
        Noise Resilience
        Modular Scalability
      Disadvantages
        Technical Overhead
        Phonon Decoherence
        Speed Limitations
    Tackling Challenges
      Mitigating Decoherence
        Superconductors
        Trapped Ions
      Simplifying Control Protocols
        Hybrid Calibration
        Error-Corrected Gates
      Enhancing Fabrication Techniques
        Superconductors
        Trapped Ions
    Conclusion
      USC unlocks new frontiers in quantum simulation, error-corrected computation, and beyond.
</code></pre> <h2 id="improvements-enabled-by-usc">Improvements enabled by USC</h2> <h3 id="fast-quantum-gate-operation">Fast Quantum Gate operation</h3> <p>When the qubit-photon coupling strength becomes comparable to resonator frequency, this enables fast gate operations. For superconducting circuits, counter-rotating terms in the interaction Hamiltonian enables virtual processes that amplify qubit-qubit couplings. For example, two-qubit gates in the nanosecond range have been proposed via multimode resonator buses operating in USC. Similarly, trapped-ion systems leverage USC to mediate entangling gates through phonon-mediated interactions, achieving high-fidelity operations at speeds unattainable in weak or dispersive coupling</p> <h3 id="scalable-architecture">Scalable Architecture</h3> <p>Superconducting quantum computers face limitations in qubit connectivity, particularly relying on nearest-neighbor interactions. Any method which enables to mitigate this drawback can push forward the superconducting circuits as a promising scalable quantum building units. It has been shown that a scalable design that enables simultaneous connections between multiple distant qubit pairs using a quantum bus coupled via dispersive interactions. The bus structure consists of orthogonal coplanar waveguide resonators interconnected by auxiliary flux qubits operating in the USC regime, leveraging virtual processes to amplify effective qubit-qubit coupling, facilitating quantum gate operations at nanosecond speeds. The authors have stated that this interaction is tunable and designed to maintain qubit coherence throughout operations.</p> <h2 id="advantages-and-disadvantages-of-ultrastrong-coupling">Advantages and Disadvantages of Ultrastrong Coupling</h2> <h3 id="superconducting-circuits"><strong>Superconducting Circuits</strong></h3> <p><strong>Advantages</strong>:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Boosted Effective Couplings</strong>: Counter-rotating terms enhance qubit-qubit interactions via virtual photons, enabling fast \(\sqrt{i\text{SWAP}}\) gates with fidelities &gt;99%.</li> <li><strong>Frequency Engineering</strong>: Multimode resonators with USC allow independent control of hopping and on-site interactions, which enables programmable quantum simulators.</li> <li><strong>Material Flexibility</strong>: Superinductors and plasmonic cavities push impedances near the quantum resistance which minimizes losses.</li> </ul> <p><strong>Disadvantages</strong>:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Decoherence Sensitivity</strong>: Strong interactions amplify sensitivity to flux noise and dielectric losses, reducing \(T_1\) and \(T_2\) times.</li> <li><strong>Control Complexity</strong>: Breakdown of the rotating-wave approximation demands advanced calibration to mitigate off-resonant driving errors.</li> <li><strong>Fabrication Challenges</strong>: Integrating Josephson junctions with high-inductance materials requires nanoscale precision in fabrication to avoid quasiparticle dissipation.</li> </ul> <h3 id="trapped-ions"><strong>Trapped Ions</strong></h3> <p><strong>Advantages</strong>:</p> <ul> <li><strong>High-Fidelity Gates</strong>: USC-mediated phonon interactions achieve fidelities &gt;99.9% for Bell-state generation, leveraging robust spin-motion coupling.</li> <li><strong>Noise Resilience</strong>: Dynamical decoupling suppresses magnetic dephasing, preserving coherence during transport.</li> <li><strong>Modular Scalability</strong>: Quantum matter-links enable ion shuttling between modules with infidelity &lt;10\(^{-7}\).</li> </ul> <p><strong>Disadvantages</strong>:</p> <ul> <li><strong>Technical Overhead</strong>: Achieving USC requires precise alignment of motional frequencies and laser intensities, complicating experimental setups.</li> <li><strong>Phonon Decoherence</strong>: Collective motional modes introduce heating rates that degrade gate performance at scale.</li> <li><strong>Speed Limitations</strong>: While faster than weak coupling, USC gates remain slower than superconducting counterparts due to finite ion transport times.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="tackling-challenges-in-ultrastrong-coupling-systems">Tackling Challenges in Ultrastrong Coupling Systems</h2> <h3 id="1-mitigating-decoherence"><strong>1. Mitigating Decoherence</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Superconductors</strong>: Employ pulsed dynamical decoupling to suppress flux noise. Optimize superinductor materials (e.g., granular aluminum) to reduce quasiparticle densities.</li> <li><strong>Trapped Ions</strong>: Use sympathetic cooling and segmented trap designs to minimize phonon heating. Implement spin-echo sequences to counteract magnetic field fluctuations.</li> </ul> <h3 id="2-simplifying-control-protocols"><strong>2. Simplifying Control Protocols</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Hybrid Calibration</strong>: Combine Quantum optimal control/machine learning with real-time feedback to tune USC parameters.</li> <li><strong>Error-Corrected Gates</strong>: Leverage bosonic codes to protect against USC-induced leakage errors.</li> </ul> <h3 id="3-enhancing-fabrication-techniques"><strong>3. Enhancing Fabrication Techniques</strong></h3> <ul> <li><strong>Superconductors</strong>: Well crafted development of plasmonic cavities can maximize \(g/\omega\) ratios while minimizing radiative losses.</li> <li><strong>Trapped Ions</strong>: Integrate photonic interconnects with ion-trap modules for scalable entanglement distribution.</li> </ul> <hr/> <h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2> <p>Ultrastrong coupling represents a pivotal advancement for quantum computation, offering exponential speedups in gate operations and enabling scalable modular architectures. While challenges in decoherence and control persist, innovations in materials science, error correction, and hybrid calibration are paving the way for practical USC-based devices. For superconducting circuits, the path forward lies in optimizing superinductors and plasmonic resonators, while trapped-ion systems benefit from advanced cooling and transport protocols. As these technologies mature, USC will unlock new frontiers in quantum simulation, error-corrected computation, and beyond.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Quantum"/><category term="computation"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ultrastrong Coupling in Quantum Computation; Challenges and Pathways Forward]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Hydra game</title><link href="https://jishnurajendran.github.io/blog/2024/hydra/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Hydra game"/><published>2024-07-15T21:01:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-07-15T21:01:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jishnurajendran.github.io/blog/2024/hydra</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jishnurajendran.github.io/blog/2024/hydra/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="hydra-game">Hydra game</h1> <h2 id="rules">Rules</h2> <ol> <li>There are Rooted graphs a. Every node has a single parent node b. Leaf is a node which is furthest with only one edge to its parent</li> <li>Pick a leaf x</li> <li>Pick an integer n</li> <li>Remove x</li> <li>Add a new n branches to x’s grandparent</li> </ol> <h2 id="example">Example</h2> <p>We consider the following rooted graph with root 1 and 3 branches from 1 $\to$ [2 3 4 ] Then from each [2 3 4] 3 more branches as shown in the Fig <a href="#fig-hydra-heads">Hydra head</a></p> <p><a id="fig-hydra-heads"></a></p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/hydra-heads-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/hydra-heads-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/hydra-heads-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/hydra-heads.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Heads of Hydra. </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="graph-theory"/><category term="graph"/><category term="theory"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fastest way to win over a hydra]]></summary></entry></feed>